(This drama is a work of fiction created based on historical facts.)
(هذه الدراما هي عمل خيالي تم إنشاؤه بناءً على حقائق تاريخية.)
(Most of the details and depictions of the characters are fictional.)
(معظم التفاصيل والصور الخاصة بالشخصيات خيالية).
Thank you for releasing Lady Yoo.
شكرًا لك على إطلاق سراح السيدة يو.
(Episode 16)
(الحلقة 16)
I said I would let that woman live.
قلت أنني سأدع تلك المرأة تعيش.
I did not say I would allow you to keep her by your side.
لم أقل أنني سأسمح لك بإبقائها بجانبك.
Now, that girl...
الآن، تلك الفتاة...
must return to Joseon.
يجب أن يعود إلى جوسون.
I am someone who keeps her promises.
أنا شخص يفي بوعودها.
I would never hurt a woman...
لن أؤذي امرأة أبداً..
with my own hands.
بيدي.
However, bad things will happen to the Joseon captives...
ومع ذلك، ستحدث أشياء سيئة لأسرى جوسون...
living in Simyang.
الذين يعيشون في سيميانغ.
Even if they were released,
حتى لو تم إطلاق سراحهم..
if someone else claims ownership of them,
إذا ادعى شخص آخر ملكيته،
they will become slaves again.
سوف يصبحون عبيدًا مرة أخرى.
If they lose their release papers,
إذا فقدوا أوراق إطلاق سراحهم،
they will become escapees and have their ankles slashed.
سوف يصبحون هاربين ويتم قطع كاحليهم.
If they hold on to fake release papers,
إذا احتفظوا بأوراق إطلاق سراح مزورة،
their ears will be pierced.
سيتم ثقب آذانهم.
Or worse, beheaded...
أو ما هو أسوأ من ذلك، قطع الرأس...
Back off. We are sparring.
تراجع.  نحن السجال.
If you lay a finger on her,
إذا وضعت إصبعك عليها
I will kill you.
سأقتلك.
I understand...
أفهم...
how you feel.
كيف تشعر.
You see, even the thought of you dying...
كما ترى، حتى فكرة موتك...
tortures me too.
يعذبني أيضا.
You want to save her?
هل تريد إنقاذها؟
In that case,
في هذه الحالة،
send her to Joseon.
أرسلها إلى جوسون.
I am glad you came.
انا مسرور بمجيئك.
I was writing a letter to send to Joseon.
كنت أكتب رسالة لأرسلها إلى جوسون.
Have you decided...
هل قررت...
to return to Joseon?
العودة إلى جوسون؟
No.
لا.
I must repay the kindness of the person who saved my life.
يجب أن أرد لطف الشخص الذي أنقذ حياتي.
I am writing that I will not be able to go to Joseon for the time being.
أكتب أنني لن أتمكن من الذهاب إلى جوسون في الوقت الحالي.
I will not leave.
أنا لن أغادر.
If I am a curse to Interpreter Lee,
إذا كنت لعنة على المترجم لي،
I am also the only one who can break that curse.
وأنا أيضًا الشخص الوحيد الذي يمكنه كسر تلك اللعنة.
If Lord Lee needs me,
إذا كان اللورد لي يحتاجني،
I will stay for as long as necessary...
سأبقى طالما كان ذلك ضروريا..
and help his recovery.
ومساعدته على الشفاء.
Your Majesty.
صاحب الجلالة.
Congratulations on your victory in war.
مبروك على انتصارك في الحرب.
We may have won,
ربما نكون قد انتصرنا
but we have lost so many soldiers.
لكننا فقدنا الكثير من الجنود.
We have yet to conquer the Shanhai Pass.
لا يزال يتعين علينا التغلب على ممر شانهاي.
(Shanhai Pass: an important region at the eastern end of the Great Wall)
(ممر شانهاي: منطقة مهمة في الطرف الشرقي من سور الصين العظيم)
Your Majesty.
صاحب الجلالة.
Enjoy the victory.
استمتع بالنصر.
This moment onwards will be crucial.
هذه اللحظة فصاعدا ستكون حاسمة.
We must prove that the Qing have been given the right to rule from the skies.
يجب أن نثبت أن أسرة تشينغ مُنحت الحق في الحكم من السماء.
To do so,
لنفعل ذلك،
we must not lose the public's favor.
ويجب ألا نفقد استحسان الجمهور.
Gak Hwa.
لا هوا.
It has been a long time since I have put you in charge of the palace women.
لقد مر وقت طويل منذ أن جعلتك مسؤولاً عن نساء القصر.
I told you not to cause any problems...
قلت لك لا تسبب أي مشاكل..
about abusing a Joseon slave woman.
حول إساءة معاملة جارية جوسون.
These days,
هذه الأيام،
how are the women of the royal household?
كيف حال نساء العائلة المالكة؟
How could I go against your order?
كيف يمكنني أن أخالف أمرك؟
I have been...
لقد كنت...
managing them well.
إدارتها بشكل جيد.
I know...
أنا أعرف...
I can trust in you.
أستطيع أن أثق بك.
Then, Your Majesty,
ثم يا صاحب الجلالة،
please put me in charge of the Joseon captives as well.
من فضلك اجعلني مسؤولاً عن أسرى جوسون أيضًا.
Gak Hwa.
لا هوا.
You are my daughter who has saved my life.
أنت ابنتي التي أنقذت حياتي.
I could...
أستطع...
even give you the whole world.
حتى أعطيك العالم كله.
I was aware...
كنت على علم...
that you were...
بأنك كنت...
hunting for Joseon captives while wearing a disguise.
البحث عن أسرى جوسون وهم يرتدون ملابس تنكرية.
However,
لكن،
you must not cross the line.
يجب ألا تتجاوز الخط.
If you treat the slaves cruelly,
إذا عاملت العبيد بقسوة
we will lose the public's support.
سنفقد دعم الجمهور.
So...
لذا...
Your Majesty.
صاحب الجلالة.
Call the royal physician.
اتصل بالطبيب الملكي.
Hurry!
عجل!
Royal physician!
الطبيب الملكي!
Where is the royal physician?
أين الطبيب الملكي؟
The news from Simyang in recent days is quite unusual.
الأخبار الواردة من Simyang في الأيام الأخيرة غير عادية تمامًا.
The Khan's illness must be severe.
يجب أن يكون مرض خان شديدا.
He is severely ill?
وهو مريض بشدة؟
The Khan would not have changed his mind due to his illness, would he?
لم يكن الخان ليغير رأيه بسبب مرضه، أليس كذلك؟
By any chance,
بأي فرصة،
he will not blame me for the Ming ship...
لن يلومني على سفينة مينغ...
that has appeared on Joseon shores, will he?
التي ظهرت على شواطئ جوسون، أليس كذلك؟
Has Choi Myung Gil, who has been taken to Simyang,
هل قام تشوي ميونغ جيل، الذي تم نقله إلى سيميانغ،
not sent any word?
لم ترسل أي كلمة؟
At first, Choi Myung Gil said he would take responsibility for everything.
في البداية، قال تشوي ميونغ جيل إنه سيتحمل مسؤولية كل شيء.
how is it that he is still alive...
فكيف وهو لا يزال على قيد الحياة..
and only watching me being interrogated?
ويشاهدونني فقط أثناء استجوابي؟
(Sim Ki Won)
(سيم كي وون)
Kim Sang Heon and Choi Myung GIl were both taken to Qing.
تم نقل كل من كيم سانغ هيون وتشوي ميونغ جيل إلى تشينغ.
The nobility will say once again...
سيقول النبلاء مرة أخرى ...
that there are no worthy men in our royal court.
أنه لا يوجد رجال جديرون في بلاطنا الملكي.
Ask for Kim Jib and Jang Chul's advice...
اطلب نصيحة كيم جيب وجانغ تشول...
and fill the royal court with their pupils.
وملء البلاط الملكي بتلاميذهم.
(Gueon: a king asking his vassals for advice)
(غيون: ملك يطلب النصيحة من أتباعه)
Now that Lord Choi Myung Gil is gone,
الآن بعد أن رحل اللورد تشوي ميونغ جيل،
Kim Ja Jeom is on his high horse,
كيم جا جيوم على حصانه العالي،
counting on his connections in Qing.
الاعتماد على اتصالاته في تشينغ.
(Kim Ryu)
(كيم ريو)
I must say, His Majesty truly frightens me.
يجب أن أقول، جلالته يخيفني حقًا.
He used to completely rely on Lord Choi and defend him.
كان يعتمد بشكل كامل على اللورد تشوي ويدافع عنه.
Now, he wants him to take responsibility for everything and pays with his life.
الآن، يريد منه أن يتحمل مسؤولية كل شيء ويدفع حياته ثمنا.
Who can we count on now?
من الذي يمكننا الاعتماد عليه الآن؟
Before I get roped into this too,
قبل أن أتورط في هذا أيضًا،
I will leave the royal court.
سأترك الديوان الملكي.
Master.
يتقن.
His Majesty is seeking your advice.
صاحب الجلالة يطلب نصيحتك.
His Majesty ordered, "Treasure Kim Jib and Jang Chul's advice,"
أمر جلالته "نصيحة الكنز كيم جيب وجانغ تشول"
"no matter what they may be."
"بغض النظر عما قد يكونون."
His Majesty said that?
قال جلالته ذلك؟
His Majesty...
جلالته...
is seeking my advice,
يطلب نصيحتي،
but I am afraid my advice will not be helpful for I lack in many ways.
لكني أخشى أن نصيحتي لن تكون مفيدة لأنني أفتقر إلى نواحٍ عديدة.
However, I would like you...
ومع ذلك، أود منك...
to go to the royal court and assist His Majesty.
للذهاب إلى الديوان الملكي ومساعدة جلالته.
But how could we go there when you decided to decline His Majesty's request?
لكن كيف يمكننا الذهاب إلى هناك عندما قررت رفض طلب جلالته؟
I agree.
أنا موافق.
Choi Myung Gil and a few other ministers...
تشوي ميونغ جيل وعدد قليل من الوزراء الآخرين...
have been dragged to Qing due to the secret interactions with Ming.
تم جرهم إلى تشينغ بسبب التفاعلات السرية مع مينغ.
Once again, His Majesty handed his loyal vassals over to the intruders.
ومرة أخرى، سلم جلالته أتباعه المخلصين إلى المتسللين.
Hence, we refuse to go to the royal court.
ولذلك نرفض الذهاب إلى الديوان الملكي.
A wealthy family that always whipped its servants...
عائلة ثرية كانت تجلد خدمها دائمًا..
was looking for someone to supervise the servants.
كان يبحث عن شخص للإشراف على الخدم.
Everyone declined the position,
الكل رفض الموقف
saying they refused to work as a supervisor under such an evil master.
قائلين إنهم رفضوا العمل كمشرف تحت قيادة مثل هذا السيد الشرير.
But one man volunteered for the job.
ولكن رجل واحد تطوع لهذا المنصب.
He whipped the servants in his master's stead...
وكان يضرب العبيد مكان سيده...
but lessened the severity of the whipping.
لكنه خفف من شدة الجلد.
So, the servants started cursing the supervisor instead of their master.
فبدأ الخدم بشتم المشرف بدلاً من سيدهم.
Who do you think truly helped the people?
من برأيك ساعد الناس حقًا؟
Those who declined the job?
من رفض الوظيفة؟
Or the man who whipped the servants,
أو الرجل الذي جلد العبيد،
knowing they would curse him?
مع العلم أنهم سوف يلعنونه؟
What should your choice be...
ماذا يجب أن يكون اختيارك...
as true scholars?
كعلماء حقيقيين؟
To a king,
إلى ملك،
his ministers are like his hands and feet,
وزراؤه مثل يديه ورجليه،
and his advisors are like his eyes and ears.
ومستشاروه مثل عينيه وأذنيه.
At the moment, His Majesty's hands and feet have been cut off,
في هذه اللحظة، تم قطع يدي جلالة الملك وقدميه،
and he has reached a dead-end.
وقد وصل إلى طريق مسدود.
What shall he do?
ماذا يفعل؟
Go.
يذهب.
Go to the royal court...
اذهب إلى الديوان الملكي..
and become His Majesty's eyes and ears.
وتصبح عيون جلالة الملك وآذانه.
Your Majesty.
صاحب الجلالة.
I guess the rumor is true.
أعتقد أن الإشاعة صحيحة
You are here alone with me.
أنت هنا وحدك معي.
And yet you are neither flushing nor stammering.
ومع ذلك فإنك لا تتلعثم ولا تتلعثم.
The rumor goes that you do not believe in marriage...
الشائعات تقول أنك لا تؤمن بالزواج..
because you are unable to function as a man.
لأنك غير قادر على العمل كرجل.
Is it wrong?
هل هذا خطأ؟
There is no way.
لا توجد طريقة.
In the past...
في الماضي...
I was awfully foolish, was I not?
لقد كنت حمقاء للغاية، أليس كذلك؟
You were very...
كنت جداً...
beautiful.
جميل.
I suppose...
أفترض...
the rumors I heard in Neunggun-ri back in the day...
الشائعات التي سمعتها في نيونجون ري في ذلك اليوم...
are true.
صحيحة.
You are here alone with me.
أنت هنا وحدك معي.
And yet you are neither flushing nor stammering.
ومع ذلك فإنك لا تتلعثم ولا تتلعثم.
They said you were a white box with 99 tails.
قالوا أنك صندوق أبيض به 99 ذيل.
It must be true.
يجب أن يكون صحيحا.
Can we stay together?
هل يمكننا البقاء معا؟
If you do not like it here,
إذا كنت لا تحب ذلك هنا،
I will go...
سأذهب...
wherever you want.
أينما تريد.
Your husband abandoned you,
زوجك تخلى عنك
despite knowing you were in Simyang.
على الرغم من معرفتي أنك كنت في سيميانج.
Hence,
لذلك،
you no longer need to stay loyal to him.
لم تعد بحاجة إلى البقاء مخلصًا له.
So please...
إذن أرجوك...
First,
أولاً،
I must speak with Officer Gu and hear his reason.
يجب أن أتحدث مع الضابط جو وأسمع سببه.
Right.
يمين.
You have a husband, after all.
لديك زوج، بعد كل شيء.
You have a husband, a father,
لديك زوج، وأب،
and a sibling too.
وشقيق أيضا.
Yes.
نعم.
I have a father, a husband, and a sibling as well.
لدي أب وزوج وأخ أيضًا.
But there is someone who saved my life.
لكن هناك من أنقذ حياتي.
For you,
لك،
I can gladly sacrifice my life.
أستطيع أن أضحي بحياتي بكل سرور.
- However... - However?
- ومع ذلك... - ومع ذلك؟
You cannot love me?
لا يمكنك أن تحبني؟
I never wished for you to die in my place.
لم أتمنى أبداً أن تموت مكاني.
What I want is...
ما أريده هو...
My Lord,
ربي،
I...
أنا...
Hey, Interpreter Lee.
مهلا، المترجم لي.
Interpreter Lee!
مترجم لي!
What is so urgent?
ما هو الأمر العاجل؟
What is the matter?
ما المشكلة؟
Khan is dead.
خان مات.
Khan...
خان...
is dead?
مات؟
Then...
ثم...
who will succeed to the throne?
من سيخلف على العرش؟
(Dorgon: Hong Taiji's half-brother)
(دورجون: الأخ غير الشقيق لهونج تايجي)
Khan's son, who has just turned six, has acceded to the throne.
وقد اعتلى العرش ابن خان، الذي بلغ للتو السادسة من عمره.
And the former king, Dorgon, has become the king regent.
وأصبح الملك السابق دورجون هو الوصي على الملك.
(Regent: a person who administers a country in place of the monarch)
(الوصي: الشخص الذي يدير البلاد بدلاً من الملك)
Then...
ثم...
are you saying the world is now Dorgon's?
هل تقول أن العالم أصبح الآن ملك دورجون؟
Yes.
نعم.
The world...
العالم...
is now Dorgon's.
هو الآن دورجون.
However,
لكن،
Dorgon did not have the power to sit on the throne himself,
لم يكن لدى دورجون القدرة على الجلوس على العرش بنفسه،
so he made a young child accede to the throne...
فجعل طفلاً صغيراً يعتلي العرش...
and had to be satisfied with being the king regent.
وكان عليه أن يكون راضيًا عن كونه الوصي على العرش.
Dorgon has not taken complete control over the Qing yet.
لم يسيطر دورجون بشكل كامل على تشينغ بعد.
Just as the former emperor...
مثل الامبراطور السابق...
buried Dorgon's mother alive as soon as he acceded to the throne,
دفنت والدة دورجون حية بمجرد اعتلائه العرش،
Dorgon will also...
دورجون سوف أيضاً...
do whatever he can...
يفعل كل ما يستطيع...
to strengthen his power.
لتعزيز قوته.
Then...
ثم...
what will happen to Joseon?
ماذا سيحدث لجوسون؟
what do you think Dorgon will do with Joseon?
ماذا تعتقد أن دورجون سيفعل مع جوسون؟
In the Year of Byeongja,
في عام بيونغجا،
there were people...
كان هناك ناس...
who wanted to kill me and make one of their people the king of Joseon.
الذين أرادوا قتلي وجعل أحد قومهم ملك جوسون.
If those people rise to power,
إذا وصل هؤلاء الأشخاص إلى السلطة،
what do I do?
ماذا أفعل؟
In the Year of Byeongja,
في عام بيونغجا،
there were people who proposed...
كان هناك أشخاص يقترحون...
dividing up Joseon amongst the princes of the Qing.
تقسيم جوسون بين أمراء تشينغ.
If those people stick to Dorgon...
إذا تمسك هؤلاء الناس بدورجون...
and gain power,
والحصول على السلطة،
what will happen to Joseon?
ماذا سيحدث لجوسون؟
We will soon be able to see...
قريبا سنتمكن من رؤية...
who Dorgon will choose to have by his side.
الذي سيختار دورجون أن يكون بجانبه.
In the next few months,
وفي الأشهر القليلة المقبلة،
whoever Dorgon reaches his hand out to,
من يمد دورجون يده إليه،
are the people who will work with Dorgon in the future.
هم الأشخاص الذين سيعملون مع Dorgon في المستقبل.
That is why...
ذلك هو السبب...
we must start moving too.
يجب أن نبدأ التحرك أيضا.
I...
أنا...
will meet General Yong Gol Dae...
سوف يجتمع مع الجنرال يونج جول داي.
and study what Dorgon has planned.
ودراسة ما خطط له دورجون.
It is a gift from the Crown Prince's heart.
إنها هدية من قلب ولي العهد.
It is a statue of Buddha...
إنه تمثال بوذا..
that the Crown Prince made just for you.
التي صنعها ولي العهد من أجلك فقط.
The Crown Prince...
ولي العهد ...
made it for me?
جعله بالنسبة لي؟
In Joseon,
في جوسون،
women spend money to make statues of the Buddha,
تنفق النساء الأموال لصنع تماثيل بوذا،
wishing for peace when their husbands go out to work.
يتمنين السلام عندما يخرج أزواجهن للعمل.
You are also...
أنت أيضا...
nervous, are you not?
عصبية، أليس كذلك؟
You do not know anything.
انت لا تعرف شيئا.
I know you are nervous.
أعلم أنك متوتر.
Since...
منذ...
the former king has become the king regent,
أصبح الملك السابق هو الملك الوصي،
(The former king: Dorgon)
(الملك السابق: دورجون)
you...
أنت...
may be purged.
قد يتم تطهيرها.
However,
لكن،
that must not happen.
لا يجب أن يحدث ذلك.
The Great Qing acquired Joseon...
استحوذت مملكة تشينغ العظمى على جوسون...
thanks to whom?
بفضل من؟
The people who should be thanked...
الأشخاص الذين يجب أن نشكرهم..
for acquiring Joseon...
للاستحواذ على جوسون..
are you and the king regent.
هل أنت والملك الوصي.
The person who knows about this fact the best...
ومن يعرف هذه الحقيقة أفضل..
is our Crown Prince.
هو ولي العهد لدينا.
Our Crown Prince...
ولي عهدنا...
trusts you...
يثق بك...
and supports you.
ويدعمك.
In the Year of Byeongja, some princes...
في عام بيونغجا، بعض الأمراء...
wanted to divide Joseon up...
أراد تقسيم جوسون...
amongst themselves.
فيما بينهم.
And some people...
وبعض الناس...
wanted to kill the king of Joseon...
أراد قتل ملك جوسون..
and rule the country themselves.
ويحكمون البلاد بأنفسهم.
However,
لكن،
only the king regent and you, General Yong Gol Dae,
فقط الوصي على الملك وأنت، الجنرال يونج جول داي،
requested for Joseon to be protected, is that not right?
طلبت حماية جوسون، أليس هذا صحيحًا؟
- That is... - Do you...
- هذا... - هل...
remember now?
أتذكر الآن؟
Therefore, in return,
ولذلك، في المقابل،
when the Crown Prince...
عندما ولي العهد..
becomes the king of Joseon,
يصبح ملك جوسون،
the rights and interests of all the products of Joseon...
حقوق ومصالح جميع منتجات جوسون...
will only be given...
لن يعطى إلا...
to you and the regent king.
لك وللملك الوصي.
Joseon...
جوسون...
with you,
معك،
you...
أنت...
with the king regent,
مع الملك الوصي
The king regent, you,
أيها الملك الوصي أنت
and Joseon...
و جوسون...
will move forward together.
سوف نمضي قدما معا.
What?
ماذا؟
Dorgon...
دورجون...
allowed the Crown Prince to visit Joseon?
هل سمح لولي العهد بزيارة جوسون؟
Congratulations.
تهانينا.
Then...
ثم...
am I also allowed to go to Joseon?
هل يُسمح لي أيضًا بالذهاب إلى جوسون؟
Can I see...
هل بإمكاني رؤية ذلك...
my mother?
أمي، والدتي؟
It is all thanks to you.
كل ذلك بفضلك.
That is not true, Your Highness.
هذا غير صحيح يا صاحب السمو.
No.
لا.
In the past, when my father passed away,
في الماضي، عندما توفي والدي،
he did not let me go to Joseon even when I offered all sorts of bribes.
لم يسمح لي بالذهاب إلى جوسون حتى عندما عرضت عليه كل أنواع الرشاوى.
But this time, you made Dorgon change his mind...
لكن هذه المرة، جعلت دورجون يغير رأيه...
and gave me a chance to visit my mother.
ومنحني فرصة لزيارة والدتي.
It has now been revealed.
لقد تم الكشف عنه الآن.
Who Dorgon...
من دورجون...
wants to join forces with.
يريد الانضمام إلى القوات مع.
Greetings, General.
تحياتي أيها الجنرال.
To thank you for allowing her to visit Joseon,
لأشكرك على السماح لها بزيارة جوسون،
the Crown Princess...
ولي العهد...
wants to send white paper...
يريد إرسال ورقة بيضاء...
You punk.
انت فاسق.
Why have you gotten on the bad side of Her Highness?
لماذا أصبحت على الجانب السيئ من صاحبة السمو؟
The king regent wants Her Highness to be one of his people.
يريد الوصي على العرش أن تكون صاحبة السمو واحدة من شعبه.
Her Highness has power over the women in the royal family.
تتمتع صاحبة السمو بالسلطة على النساء في العائلة المالكة.
But...
لكن...
when the king regent reached out his hand to her,
عندما مد الوصي يده لها،
Her Highness demanded two things.
طلبت سموها شيئين.
First,
أولاً،
she said she would not get married to a Mongolian man.
قالت إنها لن تتزوج من رجل منغولي.
Second,
ثانية،
She asked for the authority to catch Joseon's runaway captives.
طلبت سلطة القبض على أسرى جوسون الهاربين.
She is aware...
وهي على علم...
of the fact that you have been selling captives and giving me the money.
من حقيقة أنك كنت تبيع الأسرى وتعطيني المال.
If the king regent complies with her requests,
إذا امتثل الوصي على الملك لطلباتها،
Her Highness will search you first.
سوف تقوم صاحبة السمو بتفتيشك أولاً.
Then I will get caught.
ثم سوف يتم القبض علي.
How will you manage to handle this?
كيف ستتمكن من التعامل مع هذا؟
Whose orders...
لمن أوامر...
are Her Highness working under?
هل صاحبة السمو تعمل تحت؟
Is she targeting me? Or...
هل هي تستهدفني؟  أو...
does she just want a share of my wealth?
هل تريد فقط حصة من ثروتي؟
Why are you doing this?
لماذا تفعل هذا؟
What is it...
ما هذا...
that you want?
هذا ما تريده؟
You.
أنت.
You are what I want.
أنت ما أريده.
But if you do not come to me,
ولكن إذا لم تأتي إلي،
I will take you and the captives you have with you...
سأأخذك أنت والأسرى الذين معك...
and bury all of you.
ودفنكم جميعا.
If you want to bury all the captives...
إذا أردت دفن جميع الأسرى...
just to have that woman,
فقط من أجل الحصول على تلك المرأة،
you can go ahead.
يمكنك ان تمضي قدما.
Yong Yi, 30 nyang.
يونغ يي، 30 عامًا.
When I return to Joseon and harvest barley and rice,
عندما أعود إلى جوسون وأحصد الشعير والأرز،
I will certainly repay my debt.
بالتأكيد سأسدد ديوني.
Chang Sam, 50 nyang.
تشانغ سام، عمره 50 عامًا.
I will repay this kindness even in death.
سأرد هذا اللطف حتى في الموت.
Dool Ne, 50 nyang.
دول ني، إنه 50.
My sons are waiting.
أبنائي ينتظرون.
Sam Seok, 70 nyang.
سام سيوك، عمره 70 عامًا.
If you only send me back to Joseon, I will serve you as my master for life.
إذا قمت بإعادتي إلى جوسون فقط، فسوف أخدمك كسيّدي مدى الحياة.
So,
لذا،
do as Her Highness says.
افعل كما تقول صاحبة السمو.
General.
عام.
Will the king regent sit back and watch this?
هل سيجلس الوصي على العرش ويشاهد هذا؟
Do you not get it?
هل لا تحصل عليه؟
Soon, we will conquer the Shanhai Pass.
قريبا، سوف نغزو ممر شانهاي.
The Ming Empire is falling.
إمبراطورية مينغ تتساقط.
Soon, the Qing army will arrive in Beijing and the central region will belong to us.
وقريبا سيصل جيش تشينغ إلى بكين وستكون المنطقة الوسطى ملكا لنا.
So,
لذا،
the king regent does not care...
الملك الوصي لا يهتم...
if Her Highness takes the captives.
إذا صاحبة السمو تأخذ الأسرى.
I do not care...
انا لا اهتم...
if Her Highness kills the captives or not.
إذا قامت سموها بقتل الأسرى أم لا.
Now, Joseon's captives...
الآن، أسرى جوسون...
will be forgotten.
سوف ننسى.
I heard you asked to see me.
سمعت أنك طلبت رؤيتي.
Are you all finished with your urgent work?
هل انتهيت من عملك العاجل؟
My lord.
ربي.
About what happened before...
حول ما حدث من قبل...
So...
لذا...
Dorgon has...
دورجون لديه...
allowed the Crown Prince to make a trip to Joseon.
سمح لولي العهد بالقيام برحلة إلى جوسون.
You should also return to Joseon with them.
يجب عليك أيضًا العودة إلى جوسون معهم.
It would be safest to return...
سيكون من الآمن العودة ...
while the Crown Prince heads to Joseon.
بينما يتوجه ولي العهد إلى جوسون.
But you are still not fully recovered...
ولكنك لم تتعافي بعد بشكل كامل..
Do not mind my illness any longer.
لا تهتم بمرضي بعد الآن.
I do not need you to nurse me.
لا أحتاجك أن تمرضني.
But...
لكن...
Have you forgotten?
هل نسيت؟
We are...
نحن...
not anything to one another.
لا شيء لبعضهم البعض.
So, do not...
لذالك لا تفعل...
feel indebted to me in any way.
أشعر أنني مدين لي بأي شكل من الأشكال.
I have...
أملك...
clung onto you,
تعلقت بك،
and I have...
و انا املك...
gotten over a near-death experience thanks to you.
لقد تجاوزت تجربة الاقتراب من الموت بفضلك.
I have done all I have wished for.
لقد فعلت كل ما تمنيت.
So, now,
و الآن،
in my heart,
في قلبي،
there is nothing left.
لم يتبقى شيء.
So go back.
لذا عد.
My lord.
ربي.
You have...
لديك...
a lot on your mind because the Khan is dead, right?
هناك الكثير مما يدور في ذهنك لأن الخان مات، أليس كذلك؟
- That is why... - Also,
- ولهذا السبب... - وأيضاً،
I have grown tired of you who always pushes me away.
لقد سئمت منك الذي يدفعني بعيدًا دائمًا.
Yes.
نعم.
I am sick and tired now.
أنا مريض ومتعب الآن.
So,
لذا،
please go back.
يرجى العودة.
What if I do not want to?
ماذا لو كنت لا أريد ذلك؟
If I...
اذا انا...
say I do not want to go back...
أقول لا أريد العودة..
You are a married woman. Do you not have any shame?
أنت امرأة متزوجة.  أليس لديك أي خجل؟
Let us go to Joseon.
دعونا نذهب إلى جوسون.
Madam.
سيدتي.
That is what he wants.
وهذا ما يريده.
I want to do...
أريد أن أفعل...
as he wants.
كما يريد.
So, just tell her that you wish to stay here.
لذا، فقط أخبرها أنك ترغب في البقاء هنا.
How could I stay when Lady Yoo has made up her mind to leave?
كيف يمكنني البقاء عندما قررت السيدة يو الرحيل؟
Make your choice.
اصنع اختيارك.
Will you choose me or Lady Yoo?
هل ستختارني أم السيدة يو؟
That is...
إنه...
Lady Yoo, of course.
سيدة يو، بالطبع.
Jong Jong.
الشباب الشباب.
I hear you wish to join us on our upcoming visit to Joseon...
سمعت أنك ترغب في الانضمام إلينا في زيارتنا القادمة إلى جوسون...
and return home.
والعودة إلى المنزل.
Yes, Your Highness.
نعم سموكم.
My family is waiting for me in Joseon.
عائلتي تنتظرني في جوسون.
Yes, you should return home.
نعم، يجب عليك العودة إلى المنزل.
I am still deeply indebted to you...
وما زلت مدينًا لك بشدة..
for saving my son.
لإنقاذ ابني.
Once...
مرة واحدة...
His Highness the Crown Prince ascends the throne,
سمو ولي العهد يتربع على العرش
I will be sure to repay you.
وسوف أكون متأكدا من سداد لك.
You have already done so much for me.
لقد فعلت الكثير من أجلي بالفعل.
The days I spent here helping out at the farm...
الأيام التي قضيتها هنا أساعد في المزرعة...
will be remembered as the happiest time of my life.
سيتم تذكرها باعتبارها أسعد وقت في حياتي.
My lord.
ربي.
Are you inside?
هل أنت بالداخل؟
I have let the Crown Princess know.
لقد أخبرت ولية العهد بذلك.
I will be joining the Crown Princess on her upcoming trip...
سأنضم إلى ولية العهد في رحلتها القادمة...
to return to Joseon.
للعودة إلى جوسون.
That is good news.
هذه أخبار جيدة.
However, I have a lot to do,
ومع ذلك، لدي الكثير لأقوم به،
so I do not think I can see you off.
لذلك لا أعتقد أنني أستطيع توديعك.
You must truly be...
يجب أن تكون حقاً...
sick and tired of me.
مريض وتعبت مني.
All I do is inconvenience you.
كل ما أفعله هو إزعاجك.
I am ashamed,
أنا أشعر بالعار،
and I feel pathetic.
وأشعر بالشفقة.
Such a thought...
مثل هذا الفكر ...
has never once occurred to me.
لم يحدث لي مرة واحدة.
So...
لذا...
once you are back in Joseon,
بمجرد عودتك إلى جوسون،
forget all your sufferings in Simyang...
انسى كل معاناتك في سيميانج...
and live a good life.
ويعيشون حياة طيبة.
A flashy...
براقة ...
and glamorous one.
وبراقة.
Be you, Gil Chae.
كن أنت، جيل تشاي.
Yes.
نعم.
I promise you that I will live such a life.
أعدك أنني سأعيش مثل هذه الحياة.
Now, I have a goal.
الآن، لدي هدف.
I never wish...
لا أتمنى أبداً...
to cause you harm again.
لتسبب لك الأذى مرة أخرى.
Yes.
نعم.
I will return to Joseon...
سأعود إلى جوسون...
and stay brave...
وتبقى شجاعا..
to show the world...
ليظهر للعالم...
that I can live a good life.
أن أستطيع أن أعيش حياة جيدة.
Thank you.
شكرًا لك.
And I am truly...
وأنا حقا...
sorry.
آسف.
Goodbye.
مع السلامة.
Return home...
العودة إلى المنزل...
and live like a flower.
وتعيش مثل زهرة.
That is...
إنه...
all I want.
كل ما أريده.
I bet you want to kill me.
أراهن أنك تريد قتلي.
Yes.
نعم.
If you would let me.
لو سمحت لي.
You must resent me,
يجب أن تستاء مني،
but the people in Joseon have forgotten all about the captives.
لكن الناس في جوسون نسوا كل شيء عن الأسرى.
No one is even coming to us to ask to have them released.
ولم يأتي أحد إلينا حتى ليطلب إطلاق سراحهم.
So, even if something were to happen to them, no one would care.
لذلك، حتى لو حدث لهم شيء ما، فلن يهتم أحد.
No one cares.
لا أحد يهتم.
They are like...
إنهم مثل...
orphans without parents.
أيتام بلا آباء.
What I am curious about...
ما يثير فضولي...
is why you gave up on the woman you love...
لهذا السبب تخليت عن المرأة التي تحبها...
just because of those insignificant captives.
فقط بسبب هؤلاء الأسرى التافهين.
Why did you do that?
لماذا فعلت ذلك؟
Because Lee Jang Hyun...
لأن لي جانج هيون...
cannot ignore those who are insignificant and pitiful.
لا يمكن تجاهل أولئك الذين هم تافهة ويرثى لها.
How foolish.
كيف أحمق.
I am certain that your ridiculous sympathy...
أنا على يقين أن تعاطفك السخيف...
will one day hold you back.
سوف يعيقك يوما ما.
Is that what you think?
هل هذا ما تظنه؟
I do not care about others.
أنا لا أهتم بالآخرين.
Is that so?
هل هذا صحيح؟
What are you doing?
ماذا تفعل؟
Why...
لماذا...
Why did you save me?
لماذا أنقذتني؟
It would have been better for you if I died.
كان من الأفضل لك لو أموت.
Yes,
نعم،
you are a man who saves people who are falling.
أنت الرجل الذي ينقذ الناس الذين يسقطون.
Then, Lee Jang Hyun,
ثم لي جانج هيون،
will you save me as well?
هل ستنقذني أيضاً؟
I am scared.
انا خائف.
I have never...
لم يسبق لي...
lived in a world without my father.
عشت في عالم بدون والدي.
You must hate me,
يجب أن تكرهني،
but for a short while,
ولكن لفترة قصيرة،
allow me to stay next to you.
اسمح لي بالبقاء بجانبك.
Please.
لو سمحت.
Gosh.
يا إلهي.
Khan...
خان...
did not allow the Crown Prince...
ولم يسمح لولي العهد..
to return to Joseon for several years after dragging him away.
للعودة إلى جوسون لعدة سنوات بعد جره بعيدًا.
How is it that Dorgon allowed the Crown Prince...
كيف سمح دورجون لولي العهد...
to return to Joseon as soon as he became the king regent?
للعودة إلى جوسون بمجرد أن يصبح الملك الوصي؟
The Crown Princess' father had passed away,
توفي والد ولي العهد الأميرة،
so they pleaded that they could pay their last respects...
لذلك طلبوا أن يتمكنوا من تقديم احترامهم الأخير ...
So what I am asking is...
إذن ما أطلبه هو...
did Dorgon comply with the Crown Prince's request?
هل امتثل دورجون لطلب ولي العهد؟
Goodness.
صلاح.
Your Majesty,
صاحب الجلالة،
the Crown Prince has entered the capital.
دخول ولي العهد العاصمة.
Your Highness.
صاحب السمو.
His Majesty cannot see you today...
جلالته لا يستطيع رؤيتك اليوم...
for he is ill.
لأنه مريض.
If you go and wait...
إذا ذهبت وانتظرت..
Your Majesty,
صاحب الجلالة،
I am here.
أنا هنا.
I am here to pay my respects.
أنا هنا لتقديم احترامي.
All right.
حسنًا.
His Majesty did not allow the Crown Princess...
جلالته لم يسمح لولي العهد...
to visit her mother who is alone...
لزيارة والدتها التي هي وحدها ...
nor to cry in front of her father's ancestral tablet.
ولا أن تبكي أمام لوح أجداد والدها.
On top of that,
علاوة على ذلك،
the eunuchs are torturing the court ladies every day...
الخصيان يعذبون سيدات البلاط كل يوم...
as they investigate the curse of the palace.
وهم يحققون في لعنة القصر.
"The curse of the palace?"
"لعنة القصر؟"
Are you talking about the rumor?
هل تتحدث عن الإشاعة؟
The rumor has been going around for a while.
كانت الشائعات تدور منذ فترة.
Did you trace the root of the rumor?
هل تتبعت جذور الإشاعة؟
Censors...
رقباء...
need to inform His Majesty of any rumors that have spread.
ضرورة إبلاغ جلالة الملك بأي شائعات انتشرت.
But if you relay groundless rumors without even checking the facts,
ولكن إذا قمت بنقل شائعات لا أساس لها من الصحة دون التحقق من الحقائق،
how would you expect your words to carry any weight?
كيف تتوقع أن تحمل كلماتك أي وزن؟
Yes, Master.
نعم سيدي.
I will make sure to check and see if the rumor is true or not.
سأتأكد من صحة الإشاعة أم لا.
I am the Senior Sixth Rank officer of the Office of Royal Decrees.
أنا ضابط كبير بالمرتبة السادسة في مكتب المراسيم السلطانية.
According to the rumors, court ladies are being tortured in prison...
بحسب الشائعات، يتم تعذيب سيدات المحكمة في السجن..
I am investigating the rumor that has been going around.
أنا أحقق في الشائعات التي كانت تدور حولها.
Is it...
فعلا...
Father, stay still.
الأب، البقاء ساكنا.
Your arm. Yes.
ذراعك.  نعم.
Can you move your hand this way?
هل يمكنك تحريك يدك بهذه الطريقة؟
There we go.
هناك نذهب.
Am I going to meet Gil Chae?
هل سأقابل جيل تشاي؟
Yes.
نعم.
We need to meet Gil Chae soon.
نحن بحاجة للقاء جيل تشاي قريبا.
Eun Ae, do not say stuff like that anymore.
إيون آي، لا تقل أشياء كهذه بعد الآن.
Lord Yoo!
اللورد يو!
Madam is here.
سيدتي هنا.
"Madam?"
"سيدتي؟"
Father.
أب.
Eun Ae.
إيون آي.
Young Chae.
يونغ تشاي.
Gil Chae.
جيل تشاي.
You are here.
أنت هنا.
What took you so long?
ما الذي أخرك؟
Goodness.
صلاح.
Madam Bang Doo.
سيدتي بانغ دو.
Eun Ae.
إيون آي.
It is actually you,
إنه أنت في الواقع،
Gil Chae.
جيل تشاي.
You are Gil Chae.
أنت جيل تشاي.
Father.
أب.
Madam is here, Lord.
سيدتي هنا يا رب.
It is warm, right?
إنه دافئ، أليس كذلك؟
Let us sleep here tonight.
دعونا ننام هنا الليلة.
The sheets are freshly laundered.
يتم غسل الملاءات حديثًا.
Gosh, where should I sleep tonight?
يا إلهي، أين يجب أن أنام الليلة؟
Jong Jong.
الشباب الشباب.
You worked hard.
كنت قد عملت بجد.
It must have been tough.
لا بد أن الأمر كان صعباً.
So...
لذا...
Soo Ji...
سو جي...
I said I would sleep with Jong Jong tonight.
قلت أنني سأنام مع جونغ جونغ الليلة.
I came to get a pillow.
لقد جئت للحصول على وسادة.
Well, then...
حسنا اذن...
Jong Jong, sleep well.
يونج يونج، نم جيدًا.
I will.
أنا سوف.
Seriously.
بجد.
Go away.
يبتعد.
You must still be so lovey-dovey every night these days.
لا بد أنك لا تزال محبوبًا جدًا كل ليلة هذه الأيام.
That fool will not even get tired in his old age.
هذا الأحمق لن يتعب حتى في شيخوخته.
Come on. I know you like it.
تعال.  أنا أعلم أنك ترغب في ذلك.
Who, me?
من أنا؟
Me?
أنا؟
If not, then forget it.
إذا لم يكن كذلك، ثم ننسى ذلك.
It is nice.
هذا لطيف.
Officer Gu...
الضابط جو...
stays at his family home these days?
يبقى في منزل عائلته هذه الأيام؟
Yes.
نعم.
He went all the way to Simyang to find you,
لقد ذهب إلى Simyang للعثور عليك،
but he ran into a thief and had all his money stolen.
لكنه التقى بلص وسرقت كل أمواله.
He was just getting ready to head back.
لقد كان يستعد للتو للعودة.
I see.
أرى.
By the way, Gil Chae...
بالمناسبة، جيل تشاي...
Yes?
نعم؟
While you were in Qing,
بينما كنت في تشينغ،
a foreign intruder did not take advantage of you, did he?
دخيل أجنبي لم يستغلك، أليس كذلك؟
Young Chae.
يونغ تشاي.
What are you saying on such a happy day?
ماذا تقول في مثل هذا اليوم السعيد؟
Who do you take Gil Chae for?
لمن تأخذ جيل تشاي؟
It is like a dream.
إنه مثل الحلم.
Right.
يمين.
My sister is no ordinary woman.
أختي ليست امرأة عادية.
Thank you...
شكرًا لك...
for coming back.
للعودة.
Thank you so much.
شكراً جزيلاً.
Let us go.
دعنا نذهب.
I will be late tonight. Do not wait up.
سوف أتأخر هذه الليلة.  لا تنتظر.
Okay.
تمام.
Gil Chae.
جيل تشاي.
Is it really you?
هل هو حقا أنت؟
Who is...
الذي هو...
that woman?
تلك المرأة؟
Do not worry. I will take care of everything.
لا تقلق.  سوف أعتني بكل شيء
Before that,
قبل ذلك،
while you were there,
بينما كنت هناك،
nothing happened to you, right?
لم يحدث شيء لك، أليس كذلك؟
What will you do now?
ماذا ستفعل الان؟
She was taken captive...
لقد تم أسرها...
- and came back after being roughed up. - Roughed up how?
- ورجع بعد أن تعرض للخشونة.  - خشن كيف؟
Are you asking that because you do not know?
هل تسأل ذلك لأنك لا تعرف؟
You made it back alive.
لقد جعلته يعود على قيد الحياة.
You brought shame on all Joseon women.
لقد جلبت العار لجميع نساء جوسون.
I know, right?
أنا أوافق؟
How shameless.
كيف وقح.
You must have such thick skin.
يجب أن يكون لديك مثل هذا الجلد السميك.
What did you just say?
ماذا قلت للتو؟
Jong Jong.
الشباب الشباب.
What did you say? How dare you talk with that dirty mouth?
ماذا قلت؟  كيف تجرؤ على التحدث مع هذا الفم القذر؟
What? You dirty wench who has been with foreign intruders.
ماذا؟  أيتها العاهرة القذرة التي كانت مع المتسللين الأجانب.
How dare you?
كيف تجرؤ؟
I told you not to respond to barking dogs.
قلت لك لا ترد على نباح الكلاب.
Let us go.
دعنا نذهب.
Gil Chae.
جيل تشاي.
I spoke with your husband.
لقد تحدثت مع زوجك.
He has no intention of divorcing you.
ليس لديه أي نية لطلاقك.
But before that,
ولكن قبل ذلك،
he wants to hear your answer.
يريد أن يسمع إجابتك.
If nothing happened,
إذا لم يحدث شيء،
you just have to say so.
عليك فقط أن تقول ذلك.
Gil Chae.
جيل تشاي.
Did a foreign intruder really take advantage of you or something?
هل قام دخيل أجنبي باستغلالك حقًا أو شيء من هذا القبيل؟
Young Chae.
يونغ تشاي.
That man's daughter came back from being taken captive in Qing,
ابنة ذلك الرجل عادت من أسرها في تشينغ،
and when asked what happened between her and foreign intruders,
وعندما سئلت عما حدث بينها وبين المتسللين الأجانب،
she would not answer.
لن تجيب.
And yet she wants to take back her spot in the bedroom?
ومع ذلك تريد استعادة مكانها في غرفة النوم؟
Seeing how she could not prove her chastity, she must have...
نظرًا لأنها لم تتمكن من إثبات عفتها، فلا بد أنها...
If she was that afraid to die,
لو كانت خائفة من الموت لهذه الدرجة
she should have just stayed hidden.
كان ينبغي عليها أن تبقى مخفية.
How shameless.
كيف وقح.
Father.
أب.
What is "chastity?"
ما هي "العفة"؟
That hurts, Father.
هذا مؤلم يا أبي.
Gil Chae.
جيل تشاي.
When you were born,
متى ولدت،
I felt like I had the whole world in my hands.
شعرت وكأن العالم كله بين يدي.
I enjoyed all the joys in the world while raising you.
لقد استمتعت بكل أفراح العالم أثناء تربيتك.
My precious daughter.
ابنتي الغالية.
My darling girl.
فتاتي العزيزة.
However,
لكن،
you will have to live in a nightmare for the rest of your life.
سيكون عليك أن تعيش في كابوس لبقية حياتك.
What should we do?
ماذا علينا ان نفعل؟
There is nothing I can do for you.
لا يوجد شيء يمكنني القيام به من أجلك.
What should I do?
ماذا علي أن أفعل؟
No.
لا.
I will help you.
سوف أساعدك.
So that you will not live...
حتى لا تعيش...
in a nightmare for the rest of your life,
في كابوس لبقية حياتك،
your father will help you.
والدك سوف يساعدك.
Gil Chae.
جيل تشاي.
Hang on...
تشبث...
Hang on for just a little while.
انتظر لفترة قصيرة فقط.
I will prove your innocence...
سأثبت براءتك..
with my own two hands.
بكلتا يداي.
So that you will never again...
حتى لا تتكرر مرة أخرى...
be criticized by others.
أن يتم انتقاده من قبل الآخرين.
Father.
أب.
A foreign intruder.
دخيل أجنبي.
A foreign intruder is here.
دخيل أجنبي هنا.
An intruder!
متسلل!
- Master. - A foreign intruder!
- يتقن.  - دخيل أجنبي!
An intruder is here.
دخيل هنا.
A foreign intruder...
متسلل أجنبي...
Gil Chae.
جيل تشاي.
My dear.
عزيزي.
May I take a few of these daggers,
هل لي أن آخذ بعضًا من هذه الخناجر،
just in case?
فقط في حالة؟
What...
ماذا...
do you mean by that?
هل تقصد بذلك؟
Yes.
نعم.
When I was in Simyang, I was sold to a foreign intruder...
عندما كنت في سيميانج، تم بيعي إلى دخيل أجنبي...
and had to suffer utter humiliation.
وكان عليه أن يعاني من الإذلال المطلق.
I also met Lord Lee Jang Hyun there.
التقيت أيضًا باللورد لي جانغ هيون هناك.
I was released, thanks to his help.
تم إطلاق سراحي بفضل مساعدته.
What the intruders did to me...
ماذا فعل بي المتسللون...
That was not my fault.
لم يكن هذا خطأي.
Had you wanted to divorce me because of that,
لو أردت أن تطلقني بسبب ذلك،
I would not have backed down, no matter what.
لم أكن لأتراجع مهما حدث.
However...
لكن...
In Simyang, I gave my heart to Lord Lee.
في سيميانج، أعطيت قلبي للورد لي.
For that, I am sorry.
لهذا أنا آسف.
That is why I am divorcing you.
ولهذا السبب سأطلقك.
Oh, boy.
يا ولد.
(My Dearest)
(أعز ما عندي)
Will His Highness the Crown Prince return to Joseon?
هل سيعود سمو ولي العهد إلى جوسون؟
Then Interpreter Lee and Gu Jam will also...
ثم سيقوم المترجم لي وجو جام أيضًا...
Gu Jam.
قو جام.
My lord, you are here.
سيدي، أنت هنا.
But I, too, had a place I missed and wanted to return to.
لكني أيضًا كان لدي مكان افتقدته وأردت العودة إليه.
Now that Lady Yoo is divorced,
والآن بعد أن أصبحت السيدة يو مطلقة،
will she come running to you?
هل ستأتي مسرعة إليك؟
I shall return.
سأعود.
I wish to live for her from now on.
أريد أن أعيش من أجلها من الآن فصاعدا.
I had a bad craving for those rice cakes with beans.
كان لدي رغبة سيئة في تناول كعك الأرز مع الفاصوليا.
What? Rice cakes with beans?
ماذا؟  كعك الأرز مع الفاصوليا؟
Let us live like this for a thousand years to come.
دعونا نعيش هكذا لألف سنة قادمة.
Ripped by YoungJedi
ممزق بواسطة YoungJedi